Let's talk a little bit about how kids
learn English. So, this is a video in
which I'm speaking at normal speed. By
the way, this will be good practice for
your listening. Of course, the subtitles
are right there. So, hopefully you can
follow along as I'm talking about this.
I want to talk about the subject of kids
learning English. And I'm not giving a
guide or anything like that or I'm not
uh really trying to make a ton of
comparisons between us and kids. I just
want to talk about this subject in
general because it's really interesting.
I have young kids and it's fascinating
to watch them learn their native
language. It's a really interesting
process that they go through. Uh so I'm
just going to give some general notes
about this things that I've noticed and
I hope that this will be an interesting
topic for you to listen to as you
practice your listening uh just
practicing your English listening
comprehension with me. Right? So, uh,
also remember that if you like this type
of content in which I speak at normal
speed, make sure to sign up for my
advanced podcast episodes. That link is
down below. Okay, let's talk about what
it's like for a kid to learn English.
Well, first of all, as a parent, it's
kind of interesting. It's kind of hard
to realize how much your kid is learning
in just any given moment because you're
with them all the time. you don't really
notice their progress until you look
back and you say, "Wow, you know, they
didn't used to be able to or they
weren't able to say this before and now
they can say this." Or maybe you watch
old videos that you have of them and you
realize, "Wow, they couldn't say
anything back then and now they say all
these uh different things." So, it's
kind of hard to uh really track and
follow this really closely in the moment
because it happens very slowly, but um
like little by little they start to be
able to speak and uh after a while you
realize, wa they're saying all these
different things. So, it's pretty cool.
Uh my kids are growing up bilingual so
it's a different situation from the
average kid in the US because the
average kid in the US they just have to
focus on one language really. It's just
one language, one system, one
grammatical system, uh, one set of
vocabulary. That's it. However, my kids
are growing up bilingual, so that
changes a lot. It's double the words
that they need to learn, double the
rules, double the sounds, just a lot of
stuff that they have to learn. And then
separating those languages in their
brain, right? Which happens, by the way.
It happens at a very young age. It's
really fascinating to to see that
happen. But uh it's a lot of stuff that
they have to learn compared to the
average person here in the US. And so of
course their development in each
language is a little bit slower than the
average kid who's only learning one
language because they're spending all
day in that language with that language
hearing those sounds, those words. My
kids get half the time in each language,
right? So they hear Spanish from their
mom, they hear English from their dad.
So, of course, is natural that their
development is a little bit slower in
each language than just a monoling
monolingual kid, but they have like
double the, you know, things the the
vocabulary and sounds and all that to
learn. Um, so it's normal and then they
get to learn two languages, which is
really cool. So, let me talk about their
uh English and how it's been for them
learning English. By the way, my son is
like 4 and a half. My daughter is two
and a few months maybe. So, um, at first
they say single words. At first, it's
not even like proper sounds for that
word, but you can tell they're saying a
certain word. Like I remember my
daughter would always say ca instead of
car, right? She wouldn't make the R
sound. She would just say ca ca whenever
she'd have like a little toy car or
whatever. uh or like right now instead
of saying bread, she says bed instead of
bread, right? Because that br is a
little bit uh tricky. The easiest type
of sound for them to make is just like
one consonant, one vowel. So like ca da
ma, right? Those are the easiest sounds
for kids to make where it's just like
they start with a consonant and then
they end with a vowel, just one sound.
Um that's like typically what you hear
at the very beginning. you hear, you
know, ma,
you know, these types of sounds, right?
Um, but then these start to become
actual words, right? They start to be
able to say phone, for example, right?
And they'll say one words, uh, one word,
right? They'll just say one word here,
one word there. And really, they're
doing a lot of imitation. That's
basically how they're speaking. That's
how they're saying these words. They
hear you say it as the parent, and then
they say it, right? And that's kind of a
lesson for us, right? If kids learn
their first language like that,
obviously, you know, it's something that
we can um relate to as uh second
language learners, like we're really
just imitating what we hear, right? It's
not like there's some really uh complex
secret code to learning words, right? At
the end of the day, if you hear someone
say a word many times and you repeat it,
you're eventually going to know that
word, right? So that's how it works with
uh little kids as well. Their sounds
start to uh become better uh over time
as well. So they can actually say the
word clearly. Like my daughter four or
five months ago, a lot of her words were
like not properly said. Like we knew
what she was saying, but it wasn't
wellformed. Whereas like now a lot of
her words are wellformed. Like it's very
clear what she's saying. So that's kind
of cool. After the one-word utterances,
of course, they start to say two words.
these uh two-word phrases. So, for
example, my daughter might say, "Dad,
shoe, right?" So, now she's putting
together two words to create a phrase.
Obviously, it's not a correct phrase,
right? She should say daaz shoe with the
possessive s on the end. Uh but
nevertheless, it's a phrase. So, uh it's
interesting when the oneword utterances
become two-word phrases. Uh it's like an
exciting thing and they start to be able
to communicate more with that because
now the sentence is like double the
length. They can include more
information in there, right? Instead of
just shoe, it's dash, right? So there's
more information encoded into that
phrase. So the communication starts to
become a little bit more complex. Uh you
start to be able to say or just, you
know, have um conversations, let's say,
uh with them. So that's really cool.
their words continue to become clearer,
of course, especially once they're
saying two-word uh phrases like that. A
lot of times their words start to uh
just become clearer, their sounds. And
then three-word utterances um that uh is
like the next step after the two-word
utterances, right? So instead of dad
dash, it might be dad dash there or
something like that, right? So now, uh,
they're putting together these different
words and there's a lot of information
in there, but really they're including
like mostly nouns, verbs, adjectives,
maybe adverbs, uh, like the words that
really have a lot of meaning to them,
right? So, da da, she there, right?
However, they're not really including
all the prepositions and the articles
and things like that that they might
need, the possessives and these little
grammatical function elements, right?
So, they're not saying 'the' yet, right?
Uh they're not saying um I don't know um
in the house. They might just say like
in house or uh house or whatever. like
they have to start to develop the
ability to put together those little
building blocks of like articles and
determiners and stuff like that. Um, but
as their phrases get longer, you know,
after the two-word, three-word phase
that they're in, uh, then they start to
include those little building blocks,
those little function words, um, that
they weren't able to do, uh, they
weren't able to say before. So you can
see little by little how their um their
ability to communicate information
increases with more words and using
different types of words. So that's
really cool once they have all these
building blocks. Like my son for
example, right, who is older than my
daughter, he has these building blocks,
right? he can say the uh little words
that have just more grammatical function
meaning rather than like you know a noun
or a verb or whatever. Uh so once they
have these building blocks and they're
saying full sentences, they're
communicating to you well um they still
run into problems, right? They're still
young, they're still early on in their
linguistic journey, even in their native
language. And so they still run into
issues. They still make a lot of
mistakes, right? So a good one with
English uh not a good one but a good
example of this is like with inversion
with uh with questions. So for example
like I could ask how many did you do
right so I have this inversion and I put
the did right the auxiliary verb there
like how many have you done right so um
we invert our sentences we change the
order of them with an auxiliary verb in
English when we ask questions. So
instead of saying how many did you do,
my son might say how many you did,
right? So he doesn't invert it. He
doesn't have that 100% yet. I'll correct
him and then maybe he'll he'll correct
it himself. But really, he's not at the
the stage where he asks these questions
uh completely uh correctly. Other kids
his age do. Uh some don't, some do. Like
I said, my kids are bilingual, so you
can forgive them for developing a little
bit more slowly because they have all
the rules in both languages to learn,
right? So, I'm not uh very worried about
that type of thing, but um you know,
that's inversion is a good um uh like a
good example of a problem uh that they
run into. Um or maybe they do invert. I
remember hearing my um my nephew uh this
was when he was maybe like three and a
half or something like that or four. I
forget when how old he was. maybe it was
three. uh but he was trying to invert uh
or he was trying to ask the question uh
like where are they and instead of where
are they he just said where is them
right so he's thinking like where is dad
where is mama where is them right he's
just substituting them there obviously
that's wrong but you can see how he came
to that conclusion right so a lot of
these like grammar rules they're
actually understanding that there's like
these patterns and they're trying to say
things correctly but the rule rules uh
are a little bit more complicated than
what they're thinking. And so um they
can't follow these irregular patterns
and things like that. Uh like I just
heard my friend's son the other day
instead of saying I I fell uh I think he
said I I fall or I failed or something
like he needed to put a d on the end
because in his mind that's how the
grammar works, right? I walked, I
talked, I failed or I falled or whatever
he said, right? So, it's interesting to
see how they try to apply grammar, but
then the irregular rules trip them up.
So, that's pretty cool uh to see that
working uh in their brain. And you don't
really realize when they get these rules
down. It's kind of hard to remember like
when my son started to say things
correctly. It just kind of happens
gradually. Um so, again, like I said at
the beginning, it's more like when you
watch old videos of them or whatever and
you see how they used to talk and then
you go, "Oh yeah, you're saying all
these things much better now." Right?
So, um, that's a way that you notice it.
Uh, kids, uh, learn a lot of English or
whatever language they're learning. I'm
just talking about English right now.
Here in the US, they learn a lot of
English from their friends, their
environment, the people around them, and
the entertainment they watch. So, a lot
of what my son can say right now doesn't
actually come from me. Uh, most of it
comes from me, I assume, but a lot of it
comes from the things that he watches.
uh the things he hears from his friends.
Um I remember seeing something like
research done about like how impactful
it is uh like the environment around uh
a kid specifically like their friends,
not necessarily their parents, but like
what they hear their friends say, what
they hear people on the street say. This
really influences the type of language
uh that they speak, like the the type of
communication they have. So that's a
really big thing. My son says new words
and phrases all the time and I have no
idea where he learned them. I'm like,
where did you learn that? Uh I asked
that all the time because I'm like, I
know you didn't learn that from me. I
didn't say that. Um but he saw it
somewhere else or whatever. He heard it
and then you know he adopted it. So it's
um startling how many new things they
learn uh from sources that aren't you as
the parent. It's pretty interesting.
Lastly, I just want to talk about
reading. My son is learning to read
right now. And for me, it's amazing that
young children can learn how to read in
English. In other languages, this is not
necessarily the case because they're
phonetic. Like Spanish, you just learn
the sound of every letter and you can
basically learn to read like someone
who's learning to read as a second
language learner. In Spanish, they can
learn to read pretty quickly because you
just have to know the sound of each
letter, right? And even if you don't
know what the words mean, you can say
them, right? Whereas in English, nuh-uh.
Uh you probably already know by now, but
English, uh like the way that it's
written and the way that it's spoken is
extremely different. And so this system
is unbelievably complicated. And so
imagine trying to teach this to a
four-year-old, right? You're teaching
them the the sound of the letter A, but
then unfortunately the letter A can be
said like five, six, seven different
ways depending on the word, the sounds
around it, how reduced it is, how
stressed it is, like just its normal
sounds. Like they just ask these
questions like why is it said like this
now? I thought you told me that the A
makes this sound. It's super
complicated. I feel really bad uh for
kids that are in this process because it
must be so frustrating for them. Like,
dang, why is it pronounced like this?
You just told me it was like this. Why
isn't it like this? Right? Like my son,
he has an O in his name that is reduced.
Right? If you've ever watched my uh
pronunciation seminars or my listening
practice seminars, you'll know what I'm
talking about when I talk about reduced
speech, right? So, he has an O in his
name that's reduced. and he asked the
other day like, "Why isn't the O in my
name an O sound or an A sound?" And I of
course didn't uh really have the ability
to to or he didn't really have the
ability to understand when I explained
to him about the stress system in
English, but it's just super complicated
to even explain to a kid why certain
letters are pronounced certain ways and
certain words in English. This is just a
mess. And so I commend all these kids
for learning how to read at a young age
because it's really hard. Again, this is
not the case in other languages, but in
English it's extremely hard. Uh so, you
know, if that's, you know, when you hear
me talk about reduction and stuff like
that, if you want to learn more about
that, make sure to sign up for my
membership so you can get my training,
you can learn about these things. The
schwa sound, why the o is not always
pronounced a or o, but it's pronounced
h, right? Why? Right? Why does that
schwa sound come about? Right? So, if
you're interested in that, make sure to
sign up for my training. Click on the
link down below. Uh, so a lot of uh like
what they're reading uh just does not
match up to like the sounds that they're
learning. And so, they just learn to
site readad. In other words, it's in
other words, you're just learning what
the sound of a word is without really
paying attention to the individual
letters. Like the word 'the', right?
It's not t, right? That's not how you
pronounce that word. It's 'the'. So,
they just learn to sight read that.
like, okay, every time you see those
three letters, it's pronounced 'the',
right? So, that's kind of how we learn
to read. Uh, eventually, we're not
relying on our knowledge of sounds
because in English, that doesn't really
take you very far, right? So, you just
learn how to site readad all these, you
know, thousands of words. So, it's
pretty incredible how that happens. And
I'm just watching the beginning stages
of that with my son right now, and I'm
really excited to see this happen. Uh,
I'm super stoked for him to learn how to
read because I'm a big reader. It's one
of my greatest passions, hobbies. I love
reading, so I really want my son and my
daughter, of course, and any other
future kids to be big readers as well.
So, it's really fun for me to watch them
read, but I don't know how they do it.
It's like it's super complicated in
English when you're a four-year-old.
Wow. I commend them and um it's
exciting, but it's hard. So, um overall,
these are some of the notes that I have
about, you know, what I've seen from my
kids learning to speak English. Um, this
is wasn't really a guide for you, but
it's just kind of like an interesting
topic. So much of how they learn is just
related to exposure, experience,
repetition, imitating, recognizing
patterns, you know, even just the desire
to want to say certain things, right?
So, a lot of it is just like it's not
really like, you know, technical. It's
just, you know, repetition, exposure,
you know, all these different things,
desire, these other factors, right? Um,
and it's just interesting to watch all
this happen. So, I hope you enjoyed this
video. I hope it was good practice for
your listening. Remember to sign up for
my training if you want help
understanding pronouncing uh you know,
different things like that. If you want
my advanced episodes in which I speak
like I'm speaking now at normal speed,
make sure to click on the link below,
check out that membership. Okay, thank
you all for watching this video and I'll
talk to you in the next